There we go. We'll now call it over the regular City Council meeting for today's date and time.
Item 2 is proclamation declaring April 15th through 21st of 2018 Community Crisis Center Volunteer Appreciation Week.
I don't know is there anyone here from the Crisis Center? Okay.
Then I'm going to read through this and then present it to you.
Okay. Declaration of April 15th to 21, 2018 is Community Crisis Center Volunteer Appreciation Week in the city of Miami, Oklahoma, Ottawa County City of Miami, Ottawa County, Oklahoma.
Whereas Mayor Rudy Schultz and Miami City Council believe it is important to recognize citizens who distinguish themselves by various means
and who have made significant contributions in our community. Whereas the City Council believes the community crisis center volunteers are such individuals
and worthy of being recognized for their significant contributions.
Whereas community crisis volunteers have provided support and understanding for local victims of domestic violence, sexual assault and stalking.
Whereas in true partnership volunteers meet the needs of the community by supporting and serving the administrative functions of the community crisis center.
Whereas local volunteer actions are powerful force for the solution of problems in our city.
Whereas volunteering offers young and old the opportunity to participate in the life of the community and to link their talents and resources to address the issues
of domestic violence, sexual assault and stalking facing our city.
Whereas the City of Miami is committed to encouraging volunteerism among its employees, partners, businesses, organizations and citizens.
Whereas volunteers are vital to our future as a caring and productive city.
Thousands of volunteers working in our community utilize their time and talent daily to make a difference in the lives of local families.
Now, therefore, be it resolved that miracles in the Miami City Council to hear by declare April 15 through 21st, 2018.
This community crisis center volunteer appreciation week within the city of Miami.
Okay.
There's always a poll for the one here.
Item three is public input and unscheduled personal appearances.
Anyone that wants it was to address the council on any of the agenda items.
Item four is consent agenda staff is recommending items five through 13 for the consent agenda.
If there are no questions on any of those items, then I'm going to pay the motion to approve.
And a second roll call, please I'm 14 performative presentation by Crawford and Associates Ms.
Brenda White.
Hi, Brenda.
How are you?
We only see you once a year.
At least we only see you once a year.
We only see you back.
We're hearing this and the original introduction of my Crawford came up with what they call
reform.
I believe a bunch of financial ratios that help you to analyze that big book we give you
over a year that you're able to find your financial statement.
I know you all write a cover cover because you haven't solved me and I get it.
So this just kind of summarizes and puts a perspective where how you are doing.
So if you flip a word starting on pay five, this is your roll break.
And 2060, you are 17, you are 17, and 2070, and you're up to 6.0, and there's only one reason
for that drop.
But it's not a bad reason.
You refinance your bonding anticipation notes, which we're the notes that you issue to build that
stadium out there.
And that original issue and the assets related to that issue are in your NCFA.
But when you refinance that debt, because it came to maturity, it was short term finance, and
you had to refinance it.
The way you structured it, that debt is now into your government like today.
So where your debt is, and where you're asked that is into different places.
And that's the only reason for your drop.
This is your main area.
And that's what's causing the issue.
As you pay that debt off, if everything else stays the same, your numbers should go back up.
And I will tell you this drop, I'm not worried about her debt.
Other cities that we do this for, you guys look good.
You look good.
So that's kind of just overall where you fell in and you go over.
And I will go through this quickly.
If there's a pay, if you want to ask about tell me, otherwise, I'll just kind of stand it.
Thank you, seven.
The letter that I'm in strict with that position.
If we take all your assets, I'll look, all your item like the least, for all of your funds, including enterprise and government.
And we take what's left.
That isn't legally restricted.
Do we still have anything else?
And we back out to capitalize that and the debt that relates to that, what you have left.
And you went negative this year.
And the reason you did that is begins because of the debt.
You have that that $9 million worth of debt on your financial statements.
But the assets are over in that separate agreement.
So it's just kind of an odd situation.
It's not a thing that throws up a red flag to us.
It's nothings where we're saying, well, wait a minute.
What happened?
We know exactly what happened, we know what caused it, and as you pay off that debt, it's going to reverse.
So, when we had the bond anticipation notes, where was that debt sitting different?
That debt was sitting in the NCFA.
The debt was matched to the asset, and it was because of how the debt was structured.
The way the new debt is structured, being paid back with sales tax, that becomes governmental debt.
We looked at many options.
We looked at can we keep the debt in the NCFA?
To do that, we caused an accounting nightmare.
With all the funds you would have to transfer back the work forth to make it all work.
We looked at can we move the assets?
We chose not to move the assets after much discussion with staff and everybody else, because that asset is tied to a long-term lease with estate agency.
And we felt her better left off where they were originally built for tracking purposes, and in case any issue came in in the future.
So, it's just one of those odd things.
It's a periodically, these crop up and government.
Well, we would be honest, they're probably the one and the other.
But it's just one of those weird things that you felt it, too.
I would not realize, I guess.
I mean, we're always knew what the sales tax was for.
So, there was no, that's just the reality of it.
I didn't realize that the bond anticipation notes resided with the NCFA.
They did.
At the time, it has that way that structure, and it was hopeful that there would be revenue
to help pay off everything.
And there's not enough revenue to pay off a amount of debt that equals the back as you know,
off that facility.
Okay.
Page 8.
Your level of general fund and the sign for balance.
Your general fund is your main operating fund for non-utility purposes.
Okay.
And when we look at the general fund, we take away any money that's restricted.
What should have led is an assigned fund balance.
And you dropped around 17% of the balance of $5.00 to $13.00.
You're going down.
If you look at the history of the years, that's not the lowest you can.
What's causing this, what's causing this is what it do makes.
You're using your reserves to help balance your budget.
And you, over the years, have been trying to reduce the amount of transfer from the MSUA.
So, the less you transfer the MSUA, the more reserves you're going to have to use in the general fund.
Or you have to cut expenses.
So, if you want to see this number go up, those are your options.
I will tell you that 13% reserve is not bad.
Most people try to target at least 10% reserve.
So, you're above the average.
So, where do we see the fact that we're using some of our reserve funds to finance the remodel here?
Well, I haven't gotten involved that.
And I'll be honest, that's an FY18 budget.
Okay.
And I haven't looked at those numbers yet.
So, where we're finding it's in that box.
I'll be right next.
Okay.
You have to let that condition.
What is the remaining use of life in your assets?
How much of you do that?
You only have 29% of life in your assets.
But this is not a surprise to you.
It's been like that forever.
When you're buying something, you're using it for much longer than you anticipated.
That way, too.
I know you have projects on the horizon for electric water sewer.
That would cause a visit for my son.
But basically, you buy car that the anticipated paper used for five years
and keep it at the 10 to 15.
So the life of your assets is narrowed.
And that's also not uncommon in that way.
Because of limited resources.
Page 10.
This is one of the important things you do.
You're not a uniform employee pension plan.
So you're not completely your place in fire because they are in your safe life.
This is just for all your other employees.
You are about 65% funding right.
You dropped a little from last year.
What mainly caused your drop is the fact that when they do the actual burial,
every year, they can do this thing called the discount rate.
That discount rate is tied to the meanest bomb on rate.
And the meanest bomb on rate is tied to change by 1.2%.
So that affects your calculations.
65% is not great.
Everybody would like to see a higher because that just makes your hinges high and healthier.
But it's also not terrible.
It's kind of just hanging right in the middle.
So I know you guys have a bunch or a pinch of a plan about not to say it in a little bit more than that.
Actually, where it says every year, don't you?
Yeah.
So you're putting more in it to keep up.
I would be worried if you were not putting in the actual apartment.
Page 11 is okay.
You will see you have an untunned okay plan.
And for those of you who do the government, what okay is is the same as the beginning
of the county staff report calls your other postman plan of benefits.
You have a retiree who gets to stay on your health insurance plan.
And have the same premium rates as your active employees is called a blinded rate.
And basically, if there are retired rates, it should be a lot higher than some of your younger employees,
but we just have one mid blinded rate.
So that's share in that benefit.
And technically what Gatsby says is, you and the city are helping to pay for portion of their benefit.
So then I just booked this liability.
Yours is an unfair plan.
I only know two funded plans in the state of Oklahoma.
And those are your two largest cities.
So I have to booked this liability out there every year.
The fact that it's zero funded does not really bother me because most people that fund it.
I can tell you next year, you're still in a zero on here.
This year your liability is $2.7 million.
Next year it's going to go back.
I would anticipate by at least half a million if not worth.
And that's because of change in accounting standards.
implement an FYUT. And those standards basically require that they non-calculate, the OPEC
calculations, the same way they do pinching calculations with the same actual real standards.
So, it's a number. It's going to be out there and you're going to see it. But other than that,
I don't think you'll ever find it because some people can't afford to. And you just pay as you go.
Page 12. Your assets with that ratio. How much of your assets are being used to pay off
and you guys are at about 60% percent. That's not bad. You're at a little bit this year because of the new debt you took on.
So, if you take on more of your debt next year, that would go a little bit more.
But it's still not a shopping right. It's not a rate where I worry can you make your debt pay this?
Because you're just buying a debt category.
Current ratio. What is our ability to pay our short-term obligations?
Basically, our current assets will be available to you right now.
So, here are your current identities. What's the ratio? And you guys are at 3.86 percent.
You have 3.8 on more current assets than you had current $1.17. That's a good number.
And you've stayed pretty consistent over the 10 year history of doing this.
Your quick ratio, if we were just to take your cash and investments, your short-term cash and investments,
can care to your current liabilities. How many times can you cover your current liabilities?
And you can cover 2.24 times. That's not bad number at all.
Okay, that's all of the financial ratios.
There's a summary of all of those in terms of care back in the past few years on page 15.
I won't go into that. We will put those work and we will look at what we call the financial performance ratios.
Okay, 17. The third point is the change in that position.
When I take all your assets and I take all your my abilities, and I look at what is left.
That is, or take the difference in those. What is the change in those?
And this year, your change in that position will be down $9.9 million.
And again, how much is the debt you wish you? $9.4 million.
So, it's all directly related back.
So, it's a big drop. It should have an intuition after that, start coming back up.
Not, not, I will worry about that because we know exactly what the cost is.
It's not like it's being called because it's just a phenomenon.
Okay, if it's because it's simply the debt issue.
And in a period of equity, basically, are your customers in exchange for your revenue?
Or are you having to use prior and your revenues to pay for this?
This year, your current services on your type of 78% of your current services.
It's down a little part of that. It's due to the debt.
Okay, we expect to come back up.
It's not like this is consistently gone down every year.
It's not anything that's growing up right in black.
The BTA is all tied to that issue.
The BTA is self-sufficiency and current key.
Do your interpitalist electors, water sewers, sanitation,
bring you the enough revenue to pay for their costs and the answer is yes.
They covered a 119 cent.
Now, this does not include the capital.
This just includes operational costs,
so you have to live over there.
It also does not include anybody you're standing out of as
to the general fund, or to another fund.
It just includes actual cost of operations.
So now, even though you've covered more than your cost,
you're still using that money for something else.
Okay?
That service cover.
Anytime you want to bet, certainly that service cover is required.
Meaning the pleasure of revenue is for that debt.
And in most cases, your pledge revenues have to be
of 2.25% of the net of the pledge revenues in the cost.
And you guys are covering at 5.36%.
That's a great percentage.
If you're up there, if there's nothing beer,
you can't make your debt payments.
Sells tax growth.
You're down.
I need that in Sells tax.
That wasn't a stocking number.
And if I recall correctly, I'm all to grow up.
So I have my office.
I think Sells tax started showing that 20,
fit of an increase in about June of 17.
So for this report, there's only one left to die.
So Sells tax kind started recovering early summer last year.
I can't say it's recovering a great amount of statewide,
but we're starting to see a tiny bit of an increase.
Those are all the performance ratios.
And then our next set of ratios is what we call a payability.
If you go pay 24, the question is, how much is a revenue
between a rate can you control?
All you can control are the rates and charges you charge.
You can't control the price by tax that comes in.
So what percentage of the revenues that you generate can you control?
And you guys are 75% that's a pretty good number.
I mean, you're not totally relying upon Sells tax.
You're debt service load.
If you're not a capital, it stems from our building.
If you get a service cost.
You guys are at $5,000, that's great.
I mean, that's a great number.
I just think that fluctuating a little bit next.
You're going to do this to actually start making payability on it.
But it's not going to go up right now.
Okay.
Your next release line.
I think it is.
I'll relate to what we call bonded debt per capita.
And yours is zero.
For you to have bonded debt, you have to issue general obligation bonds.
The only way to save a local comment.
You can issue general obligation.
is to finance a court-assessed judgment, or to go to a vote of the people with capital
projects to be able to issue a geo-bond that then goes and is financed through proper
attacks. You have no general obligation there. You are not electing a proper
attacks on your citizens for anything at this point. So these three slides are
zero simply for that fact. It's a financing source you have out there, the
country, which can't really do, but it would have voted to be. So then over to page 29,
you're local self-tapped rights, and say the same, it's very comparable to other communities
in the moment. You're not the highest number of those. None of them really take care of them.
And that is the performer in the next show. And I said I would be great, but the week you get
really into this in a lot of details. I'll answer questions, or if you have questions later, you can
email me, comment if you're willing to send them out. So we just like to be able to give you a
perspective of, we take that paperwork and we write it down, overall how do we do? You guys
have been pretty good. What's the amount of the average one time I thought of in the past, you
said, here's how you're average. And they're about to, I was compared to others, I don't know,
that you're fucking, averaging all of these together. Well that's what page five is. When we
average it all it comes out to about a six. So we've been the highest in age. Yes. But I can tell you
I've seen these down in the ones that we've been also. And I think of this, it's nice if
they can, if you have a hundred different accounts, look at it, they might all get something different.
This is just the way we come up with with a way more easily, can you take my information?
Okay. Question? As we go out to bond to do the structure, how is that going to affect your
bond breaking agency for actual literature and what financial statements? And they will take
a lot of different factors into account. I can tell you for the bond to do this in FY 17, you've got
to get ready. And I don't see anything in the 17 financials that would cause the bond rating
aid it to make anything go right down. We're going through that process right now in the $9 for the
eight and a half million dollars that you just authorized. So we'll be going through that same process
and bringing you that information when we actually issue those bonds. But it won't affect the
performance or rating. Our next step. Is the SUA included in that? Yes. Well, we look at this,
besides where I just talked about the general fund, everything else that's citywide,
it includes everything. So the SUA is going to be occurring that way. Yes, you are exactly. Yes.
And so, if you're just asking if that debt will affect, then it will affect your overall numbers.
Because it's going to affect your amount of rating cost or the...
All the links are in the description.
Yourster.
Let's do it.
I can do it.